Register of the Benjamin F. Holman Papers, 1966-1977
Hoover Institution Archives
Benjamin F. Holman Papers
1966-1977
85032
Hoover Institution Archives
13 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope (5.5 linear feet)
Correspondence, memoranda, racial incident case reports, other reports, pamphlets, press releases, and clippings, relating to desegregation of schools and other facilities in the U.S.; racial or ethnic friction involving black, Hispanic, American Indian and other minority communities; and efforts of the Community Relations Service to resolve such situations.
Holman, Benjamin F., 1930-
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1985.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1930, December 18 Born, Columbia, South Carolina
1948-1950 Student, Lincoln University, Pennsylvania
1952 B.S., University of Kansas
1954-1957 Postgraduate work at University of Chicago, Illinois
1952-1962 Reporter, Chicago Daily News
1962-1963 Commentator, WBBM-TV, Chicago
1963-1965 Reporter, assignment editor, CBS News, New York City
1965-1968 Assistant director for media relations, Community Relations Service, United States Department of Justice, Washington
1969-1977 Director, Community Relations Service
1968-1969 Producer, NBC News
1978- Professor of journalism, University of Maryland
United States. Community Relations Service.; United States. Dept. of Justice.; African Americans.; Civil rights--United States.; Education.; Hispanic Americans.; Indians of North America.; Minorities--United States.; School integration--United States.; United States--Politics and government.; United States--Race relations.
- CLIPPING FILE, April 1969-June 1970. (Box 1)
  General note
  Clippings collected from various newspapers, arranged chronologically
- COMMUNITY RELATIONS SERVICE (CRS) INTERNAL OFFICE FILE, 1969-1977. (Box 1-2)
  Case reports, memoranda, office documents, rosters, speeches and writings, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1969-1977. (Box 3)
  Letters and memoranda with individuals and agencies outside the Federal government and with departments and individuals within the Federal government but outside the Justice Department, arranged chronologically
- JUSTICE DEPARTMENT COMMUNICATIONS, 1968-1976. (Box 3-4)
  Articles, memoranda, press releases, reports, speeches, arranged alphabetically by office or position
- PERSONAL FILE, 1969-1977. (Box 4-7)
  Affidavits, articles, biographical sketches, clippings, correspondence, daily schedule, memoranda, office records, pamphlets, schedules, speeches, travel itineraries, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- SUBJECT FILE, 1966-1977. (Box 7-13)
  Annual reports, cartoons, clippings, congressional records and legislation, correspondence, handbooks, memoranda, office records, pamphlets, reports, arranged alphabetically by subject
- PHOTOGRAPHS. (Envelope A)
  7 photos of Benjamin Holman.
- CLIPPING FILE, April 1969-June 1970
  - General (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
- COMMUNITY RELATIONS SERVICE INTERNAL OFFICE FILE, 1969-1977
  - General (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Case reports
    - Alerts (Folder 4)
    - Assessments (Folder 5)
    - Activity summaries (Folder 6)
    - Followups (Folder 7)
  - Crisis activities (Folder 8)
  - Memoranda
    - General (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Associate Director, Includes a memorandum about the American Indian Movement convention at Standing Rock Sioux Reservation, 1973-1974. (Folder 2)
    - Chief Counsel, Includes weekly reports on desegregation activities and a memorandum about the Louisville desegregation case, 1975-1977. (Folder 3)
    - Goldenrods (memoranda from Holman to the staff), For topics, see appendix, 1969-1977. (Folder 4-11)
  - Monthly region reports, November and December 1976 (Folder 12)
  - Rosters (Folder 13)
  - Speeches and writings by CRS officials other than Holman (Folder 14)
  - Staff time reports (Folder 15)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1969-1977
  - Correspondence with agencies and individuals outside the Federal government
    - Includes William J. Raspberry and Roy Innis, 1969-1970. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1971-1972 (Folder 2)
    - Includes clippings, 1973-1975. (Folder 3)
    - Includes William J. Raspberry, 1976-1977. (Folder 4)
  - Correspondence with departments and individuals within the Federal government but outside the Justice Department (Folder 5)
- JUSTICE DEPARTMENT COMMUNICATIONS, 1968-1976
  - General
    - General (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Press releases (Folder 7)
    - Speeches and writings by Justice Department officials other than Holman. Includes speeches by Richard G. Kleindienst, Richard L. Thornburgh and William B. Saxbe (Folder 8)
  - Assistant Attorney Generals, 1969-1976 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Attorney General, Topics include student unrest, desegregation in Boston, Detroit and other schools and American Indians. Includes weekly reports on significant developments nationwide, 1969-1976. (Folder 2)
  - Deputy Attorney General, Topics include the IMAGE project, American Indians, Mexican-Americans and Boston school desegregation, 1968-1976. (Folder 3)
  - Law Enforcement Assistance Administration (LEAA), Includes a study of LEAA and a critique of the study, 1969, 1976. (Folder 4)
  - United States Attorneys. Includes memoranda about civil disturbances in Illinois (Folder 5)
- PERSONAL FILE, 1969-1977
  - General. Includes correspondence, memoranda, clippings, pamphlets, daily schedule, articles and affidavits regarding staff complaints
    - General and Includes materials on Holman's reappointment as director and copy of a speech by Holman to the Civil Rights Oversight Subcommittee on the proposed budget cuts for CRS, 1969-1973. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Includes article by Holman on mediation, 1974. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Includes copy of a speech by Holman on minority/majority coalitions, 1975. (Folder 2)
    - Includes letter from Jimmy Carter accepting Holman's resignation, 1976-1977. (Folder 3)
  - African trip, 1972 (Folder 4)
  - Articles and appearances (Folder 5)
  - Biographical sketches (Folder 6)
  - Clippings about Holman and CRS
    - General (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - 1969 (Folder 2-3)
    - 1970 (Folder 4-5)
    - 1971 (Folder 6)
    - 1972 (Folder 7)
    - 1973 (Folder 8)
    - 1974-1976 (Folder 9)
  - Congratulatory letters (Folder 10)
  - Interview with John Slawson (Folder 11)
  - Itineraries (Folder 12)
  - Speeches and writings. Topics include desegregation, CRS, black community and press, LEAA, racial conflict, police, Hispanics Americans, Black colleges, civil rights, racism and the media
    - General. Includes correspondence, schedules and background information (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Typescripts, 1969-1970. (Folder 2)
    - Typescripts, 1973-1977. (Folder 3)
  - Travel notes, Includes itineraries, correspondence and background information, 1973-1976. (Folder 4)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1966-1977
  - General (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Aldritch, Alexander (Folder 6)
  - Bicentennial (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Black Americans (Folder 2)
  - Brookings Institution
    - Correspondence (Folder 3)
    - Handbooks (Folder 4-5)
  - Bunche (Ralph) United Nations Association Program (Folder 6)
  - Business community (Folder 7)
  - Civil rights legislation (Folder 8)
  - Coalition on Cable Television (CATV) (Folder 9)
  - Community Anti-Crime Assistance Act of, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Community Relations Service
    - Annual reports (Folder 2)
    - Complaints of misconduct (Folder 3)
    - History of CRS for Johnson Library Project (Folder 4)
    - Origin and development of CRS (Folder 5)
    - Promotional materials (Folder 6)
  - Congress (Folder 7)
  - Consultants (Folder 8)
  - Crisis Reporting System (Folder 9)
  - Desegregation
    - General (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Desegregation handbook, Dayton public schools, Ohio (Folder 2)
    - Mark Twain Junior High School for gifted and talented, New York (Folder 3)
    - Resource book from CRS desegregation workshop, December 11-12, 1975 (Folder 4)
    - St. Louis County, Missouri (Folder 5)
    - Southern schools (Folder 6-7)
    - Wilmington, Delaware public schools (Folder 8)
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Federal government (Folder 2-3)
  - Hispanic-American "Brown Program" (Folder 4)
  - Human relations commissions (Folder 5)
  - Justice Department
    - Attorney General annual reports, 1973, 1974 (Folder 6-7)
    - Budget (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - KAYE radio station, Puyallup, Washington (Folder 2)
  - Labor and civil rights (Folder 3)
  - Media - advertising campaign (Folder 4)
  - Media projects (Folder 5)
  - Nixon, Richard (Folder 6)
  - Planning, Policy and Program Development, Office of (OPD) (Folder 7)
  - Police (Folder 8)
  - Police recruitment (Folder 9)
  - Prisons (Folder 10)
  - Race and race relations (Folder 11)
  - Rumor control centers (Folder 12)
  - Special Headquarters Alert Response Program (SHARP) (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Staff management plan (Folder 2)
  - Staff training (Folder 3)
  - Student unrest (Folder 4)
  - Tacoma, Washington (Folder 5)
  - Tension, Racial. Report, Summer 1972 (Folder 6)
  - Transition to Carter administration, December 1976 (Folder 7)
  - Tuller, Charles (Folder 8)
  - Wounded Knee, Pine Ridge Sioux Reservation (Folder 9)
- PHOTOGRAPHS (Envelope A)